hello everyone and welcome to the
mindscape podcast I'm your host Sean
Caroll so here's a question given a
problem how do you find the solution to
that problem this is one of those
questions that sounds deep or profound
or something like that but in fact you
might worry it is a little bit too
abstract how can we hope to understand
how in perfect generality to find the
answer to a problem if you haven't given
me a bit more information about what
kind of problem it is you're talking
about but it's not so abstract that we
can't make some progress you know in
general how do we in fact go about
solving problems sometimes hopefully
indeed you'll find a problem that
resembles another problem a problem that
you've seen before so you can either use
or maybe adapt the kind of solution that
you already knew about other times you
know nothing about the context of a
problem so maybe you'll just try some
things randomly sort of flail about just
get some
information these kinds of questions as
abstract as they are turn out to be
frighteningly relevant to things like
building artificial intelligence right
when you turn on the computer and
there's no software on it yet the
computer doesn't have any pre-existing
strategies for solving problems you have
to choose how to build them in so how
should we go about figuring out the best
way in different contexts to solve
problems well one thing to do is to look
at what actual human beings actually do
the lesson of today's conversation with
Allison gnik is that human beings use
different ways to solve problems in
different life stages there's a way that
we do it when we're adults when we're
flourishing in the prime of life and
there's a different thing that we do
when we're children or babies very
roughly speaking babies are a little bit
more creative a little bit more free
flowing they just try a whole bunch of
things their attention is hard to pin
down you might have noticed that if
you've ever dealt with babies
and that's a feature not a bug the fact
that babies have trouble focusing their
attention on something is a reflection
of the fact they're trying to learn
about the World by interacting with it
in many different ways whereas adults
are optimized for something different
hopefully by the time you're an adult by
the time you're in your 30s you've
learned a lot about problem solving
strategies and you're more about
perfecting the methods that you already
know rather than flailing around
randomly and learning new ones not that
you can't do it not that it's impossible
but you're better at some techniques
than others and maybe who knows we sort
of brush upon the possibility in the
conversation that later in life once
you're past your Prime uh reproductive
cycle for example you can go back to
being less hidebound I mean maybe that
would be ideal we all know people who
don't quite live up to that but you
serve different purposes I I guess the
overarching lesson here is that there's
a division of labor not only between
different human beings working in groups
but even between different life stages
of single human beings and as we'll talk
about we do in fact learn some lessons
that might be very very relevant to Ai
and programming computers and thinking
about how we should best approach
understanding the world that's what
we're here to do here at mindscapes so
let's
[Music]
go Alison gnik welcome to the mindscape
podcast happy to be here so one of the
things I guess we could start with from
your work that that I've derived is the
idea that little children kids babies
whatever um maybe shouldn't just be
thought of as unformed adults right that
they actually think in a different way
is that an okay way to put it yeah
that's exactly the right way to put it
so I think a lot of people have always
thought
about the
35-year-old um psychologist or
philosopher is sort of the height of all
of intelligence and then we just build
up to that amazing person as we get
older and then we fall off off as we get
older but of course that doesn't make
very much sense from an evolutionary
perspective and in fact I think what's
come become clearer and clearer is that
children are really fundamentally a
different kind of intelligence than than
typical adults are um and there's also
some interesting questions about Elders
having a different kind of intelligence
as well so it's more like a kind of
tradeoff between different kinds of
intelligences than it is having one
magic thing which is called intelligence
that we have more of or less of and that
we have less of to begin with and more
of uh more of later on and an idea that
I've been working on a lot is an idea
that actually comes from computer
science which is the idea of a trade-off
between different kinds of intelligences
um and in particular a trade-off between
what's called exploit intelligence and
explore intelligence and what I've
argued is that childhood is really about
this kind of exploration intelligence
which is not just different from but
even intention with uh exploit
intelligence and now I have to say when
I first started making these sets of
arguments I was as you could tell from
that last comment I was a little snarky
about those you know 35y old
philosophers and
psychologists um U sitting and thinking
that they were the the Apex of
intelligence but since my own children
have gotten older and I have more
grandchildren I now I sort of reverse
that I my main feeling now is oh my God
those poor 3 5y olds the the children
and the grand moms are getting to do all
the really fun human stuff um what of my
other slogans is that we're basically
human up till puberty and after
menopause and in between we're sort of
glorified primates we're doing the
things that all the primates do we're
finding our way in the dominance
hierarchy and we're mating and we're
getting resources and all that stuff and
it's only when we're little and we're
old that we get to do things like theory
of mind and discovery about the world
and causal inference and cultural
transmission and uh large scale
storytelling all the things that really
make us human so now I feel like okay we
Grand moms and kids to just keep quiet
the fact that we're having all the fun
and then the 35 year olds are having to
do all the work and so this is going to
you know be a preview for what's to come
in the in the conversation but that's
basically because we're in that
exploratory phase early on and and in
what is nominally thought of as the
prime of our adult lives we're more
focused right we have tasks and we're
very good at doing those tasks but we're
less good at being flexible and creative
about things so so there's this idea uh
that comes from um computer science
about trying to Sol what happens when
you're trying to solve what's called a
high-dimensional task that means that a
problem that has lots of different
possible solutions that vary along a lot
of different dimensions and one thing
you can do is you can just kind of tweak
what you're already doing a little bit
and see if that makes things a bit
better and that's a very efficient
effective way of trying to solve the
problem so just change where you are a
little bit see if that makes it better
if it does then then try something else
um and that's the essential exploit
strategy that's the grown-up strategy
here's the thing that I need to do I'm
going to focus on trying to do it but of
course the problem with that is that
there might be another solution that's
much further out in the space that's as
it were you know in the far reaches of
the box at least if not actually out of
the box um and if you just keep making
these little tweaks you're never going
to get there but what you so what you
could do is you could Bounce Around try
lots of things sort of independent of
whether they're you think they're going
to be useful or not just just try things
just see how the world Works um and in
uh computer science they talk about this
is the difference between a low
temperature search think about it your
your audience will will get this analogy
right um think about it as if it was a
molecule of air that's just either going
very slowly or bouncing randomly around
in the space and the interesting uh uh
solution that comes out of computer
science is that the best strategy so
these two things trade off against each
other right like you can't do both at
the same time so which should you do and
it turns out the best strategy is start
out with a big bouncy random wild search
even though of course that's going to
take a lot longer and you're going to
spend a lot of time thinking about
things that actually aren't going to
help you and then gradually cool off to
uh the more focused search and people in
uh in computer science talk about this
as simulated analing it's like what
happens when you heat up again your
audience should know this what happens
when you he heat up metal and cool it to
make it more robust um and what I think
is that childhood is essentially
Evolution's way of doing simulated and
eiling so if you think about those two
descriptions there's one way that's
focused and oriented towards outputs and
then there's this noisy bouncy random
kind of way behav you could sort of
pretty immediately think which one fits
your four-year-old better yeah and the
thought is that that even though that
might look from some perspectives as if
it's a deficit because the kids are
saying weird crazy things they're often
strange pretend land they they do things
that don't seem to make sense at first
if you're in explore mode then that's
really the thing that you want to do
more than anything else so of of course
in some ways what this means and we've
actually shown this empirically is that
children are more creative than
grown-ups at least sometimes so for
instance we've done a bunch of studies
where we give children and grown-ups a
problem that either has a pretty obvious
there's a there's an obvious solution
you could try or a much less obvious
hypothesis one that it's to start out
with is less likely and what we've
discovered is that when the solution is
the more likely the more obvious one as
you might expect the grown ups are
better at getting to the solution but
when it's the unlikely hypothesis
four-year-olds are actually better than
say college undergraduates at getting to
the right uh at getting to the right
solution so in some ways the
four-year-olds are are more creative
than adults but the trouble is if you
look at what we think of when we think
about creativity and adults it's really
got two pieces so it's not really easy
to compare so if you look at what uh a
creative solution for an adult the first
part is generate lots of
possibilities and then the second part
is pick out the one that's good right
pay attention to the ones that are good
and not the ones that aren't and that
first part generate lots of solutions
think of lots of possibilities that's
where the kids really Excel but for
adults you also have to have the part
about you also have to have the part
about choosing the right solution in the
end and that's the part where those
executive uh exploit capacities seem to
be more useful so um the Great
philosopher John lo I Sean I know you
have the chair of natural philosophy who
was a great natural philosopher um said
that there were two faculties for human
intelligence one was the faculty of wit
and one was the faculty of judgment so
the faculty of wit was generate lots of
new ideas and the faculty of judgment
was pick out which ones were actually
good ones and kids seem to have a
tremendous amount of the faculty of wit
not quite so much of the faculty of
judgment fair enough but okay if we're
giving Evolution credit for coming up
with this you know nice division of uh
temporal labor over our lifetimes let's
let's face up to the fact that kids are
pretty helpless like human babies they
take a long time to be able to fend for
themselves could you talk a little bit
about how that fits in with what we know
about other species and whether or not
it's like an accident or actually
optimizing something yeah it's
interesting because um if you look
across an incredibly wide range of
species even including insects and
there's some arguments that this is true
even for for plants but certainly true
for all the primates and for uh and for
mammals in general you see this really
striking correlation between how smart
perhaps from a human perspective but how
how how good an animal is at learning
how large its brain is how much it uses
its brain um and how long a childhood it
has um so you see it the first the first
context in which people notice this was
with birds so if you look at birds like
Corvett or crows very very smart birds
um they spend as long as a year or two
being fledglings needing to be taken
care of whereas if you think about like
the domestic chicken chickens are mature
within a couple of weeks and although
this gets me in trouble with Chicken
Lovers and everywhere they're not very
bright there or a better way of putting
it is they're extremely good at doing
the things that they do well like
pecking for grain and they're very good
at doing those from the time they're
born they're not so good at learning and
if you think about it from this sort of
explore exploit perspective that kind of
makes sense so if you're going to be a
creature that lives in a changing
unpredictable environment that has to do
lots of new things um you're going to
need a period to be able to do that
exploration before you can exploit and
that means that in that period you're
going to be really bad at doing things
you're going to be helpless and you're
going to need other you're going to need
the other adult members of the species
to look after you make sure you stay
alive make sure you have enough calories
to to um uh you have enough calories to
fuel All of This ferocious learning
that's going on um and that seems to be
sort of The evolutionary strategy I the
calories are kind of a nice uh a nice
part of this because it turns out that
if you look at how many what percentage
of your calories your brain uses up even
as an adult you know 20% of your
calories are going to your brain which
means that your brain is you know an
expensive Computing Gadget but when you
were four 60% in fact almost 70% of your
calories were going to your brain so
basically you know your average
4-year-old is like like a you know
something out of Doctor Who or Science
Fiction it's basically this giant hungry
brain that's going around the world
hypnotizing us into feeding it both a
bunch of peanut butter sandwiches so its
brain can work and a bunch of data so
its brain can work so that's interesting
because you're pointing to an
explanation that is not purely physical
or even mostly physical it's not about
brain size or anything like that but
that uh if we allow ourselves to
poetically um attribute forces of
natural design to intelligent design
rather to Evolution um the this sort of
planned difficulty in taking care of
oneself is actually serving the purpose
of letting the kids explore be creative
and that's supposed to pay off later in
life that's right so the the thought is
and you know of course as always in
biology and evolution it's complicated
and it's connected to other kinds of
aspects of animals and there are smart
animals who don't have a long childhood
like uh um cephalopods octopuses for
example um uh different kinds of animals
seem to solve this explore exploit
problem in different ways sometimes
insects and uh for instance seem to do
it by kind of division of labor among
some ants are some ants and bees are
explorers are scouts and some of them
are workers who are actually doing
things so there's different ways of
solving it but it does seem like this is
a strikingly general and common solution
among a very very wide range of of
species and that suggests that it's got
this adaptive it's got this adaptive
value is this division of labor thing
um a general Fe teacher I I think I
remember it was Michael M Krishna who I
had on the podcast and who mentioned
this experiment which I guess is famous
among psychologists where H uh human
children and chimpanzees were asked to
poke sticks into a box and get a reward
and then when it's revealed that one of
the sticks isn't doing anything uh the
the children didn't learn oh sorry the
yeah the children didn't learn and the
chimpanzees did because the children
were trusting the grown-ups right yeah
and of course that's another dimension
of having this long uh having this long
childhood and having this particular
kind of intelligence which is that we
are also social and cultural Learners so
we pass on information from one
generation to another in a way that no
other other animals do it more simply
but they we do more of it than any other
animal does and again a lot of that
social transmission is taking place in
the context of you know caregivers
people who are who are moms and dads who
are helping the kids but it's
interesting because that is a famous
experiment but it's worth pointing out
that um again there's this trade-off so
if you just imitate what the other
people around you are doing then there's
kind of no point because you're not
going to make any progress um so
somebody along the line has to actually
innovate as well as imitating and
there's a bunch of work we've done some
of it and other people have as well that
show that children are when they're
imitating they're kind of balancing well
what do I think about how this actually
works and what do I think about the
person who's actually uh demonstrating
it to me so for example there's a lovely
experiment where if you have the
experimentor says I'm going to show you
how this works the children are much
more likely to do the kind of
overimitation that you've described so
they'll just do what the experimentor
did but if the experimentor says gee
look at this I don't know how this works
do you know how this works
then the children are much more likely
to explore including exploring in these
kind of un unlikely ways and vice versa
we did some experiments that showed that
if you actually show get let children
discover something about a machine for
instance a lot of our experiments depend
on this wonderfully simple inexpensive
machine the blicket detector it's a
little box that lights up and plays
music when you put some things on it and
not others and it costs like I don't
know $29.99 or something it's a nice
nice nice from the grant perspective uh
and it's it's been it's it's been
extremely productive so if you do
something like present the child with a
little box let them play with it and
they see that say red blocks make it go
and then you have an adult who says oh
blue blocks make the detector go the
children it's interesting they'll just
com exactly split the difference between
what they see themselves and what the
adult says so they won't just rely on
what they do see themselves they won't
just rely on the adult but they they'll
produce one um they'll produce one
solution or another kind of in
proportion to the probability of those
two of those two solutions so I I do
think the fact that we're social beings
but that in the course of cultural and
social Evolution Michael might have
talked about this we have to balance
imitation and Innovation and it's quite
complicated to to do that that I think
that also plays a role in the special
intelligence of children well it makes
me think very much of being being an
adviser to students right uh especially
graduate students where you want to say
look please do be creative and come up
with new ideas but please also read some
of the literature and there's a there's
a balance there you don't want to just
slavishly follow what other people have
already done yeah I mean I think that
the one of the interesting things that
we're working on now um is thinking
about caregiving thinking about what
happens as you take care of someone else
and that's been very that the and
particularly think about the
intelligence of caregiving thinking
about how hard it is to figure out what
you should do as a as a teacher or a
therapist or a parent that will allow
the person you're caring for to become
autonomous right you don't want them to
just imitate what you do you don't want
them to just do the same thing but you
also don't want them to get into trouble
you don't want them to do do stupid or
dangerous things and how I think it's
really interesting about how caregivers
manage to walk that line no matter what
kind of context uh they're in whether
you're thinking about being a you know a
grandmother of a 2-year-old or you're
thinking about being a supervisor of
post talks it's the same it's
fundamentally the same problem and it's
having those caregivers that enables a
lot of that cultural transmission to
take place one of the interesting things
that has come out that I've been writing
and thinking about recently is that
actually grandmothers seem to be playing
a grandmothers and grandfather fathers I
always talk about grandmothers
egocentrically seem to be playing a
particularly important role in that kind
of cultural transmission so there's
quite a bit of anthropological evidence
that when you look at um you know who
gives the songs who gives the stories
who tells you the big aspects of the
culture it's more likely to be older
people than than parents so the parents
are kind of trying to deal with the
everyday keep the kids alive keep fed
and it's actually the grandparents who
are you know in my case telling telling
um um reading naria books and singing
old Broadway show tunes and and doing
things that are things that are
especially designed to serve this
function of cultural transmission and of
course just as we have this
exceptionally long childhood we also
have this long post-menopausal
grandmotherhood elderhood uh which is
not characteristic of other uh other
animals except except interestingly for
orcas so orcas are one of the few
examples of a mammal that also continues
to live for some substantial period of
time after menopause and has
grandmothers that live with a pod and
what the grandmothers do is pass on
information about what to eat and how to
function so especially when things get
get short the grandmothers are the ones
who lead the Pod out to oh okay I
remember you know 20 years ago there was
Krill in this in this site and um and
help to help the the grandchildren uh
the children and grandchildren to
survive and I think that's another
really nice sense of a kind of
intelligence that's different from what
we think of as the standard grown-up
intelligence that sounds almost too
adorable to be true how sure are we that
the uh that the killer whales really uh
put so much responsibility in the
grandmother's um hands what what I like
about this is what the C what it shows
is the really important thing to pass on
is recipes right the thing that the
grandmothers that's the thing that the
grandmothers are designed by Evolution
to to
do and the the uh I I just again with
the adviser thing just it's on my mind
we can be egocentric a little bit that's
okay um I do think a very very common
mistake in dealing with students is that
the older wise folks are sometimes too
good at saying why a good why a new idea
won't work right right and and I mean
are you are you hinting that maybe I'll
get better at that as I get older I'll
be more open to the exploration well I
think that's definitely one of the uh
that's definitely one of the features of
of Elders that seems to be important and
you know again to use the analogy of the
students I think part of the reason for
that is that the 35y old caregiver also
has their own agenda right so they want
to make sure that they get the results
that they need for the Grant and the
more the older person can sort of say
okay I'm I've gotten what I need I can
be um more open to the possibility that
this younger generation is actually
going to do well now of course there's
big individual differences among
grown-ups about how much How likely they
are to to do that or not um but it's
interesting that even if you there's a
little bit of evidence that even if you
look at adult scientists and you know
one of my one of my other slogans is
that it's not that children are little
scientists it's that scientists are big
children and I almost always get a round
of applause you know if I if I say this
at fery lab or or you know larence
Berkeley lab everybody sort of agrees
with that um uh and one of the the
there's a little bit of empirical
evidence that shows for instance that
the labs that get The Nobel prizes are
the ones where something unexpected
happens so what happens when you do your
you do your experiment and what comes
out is like totally weird not what you
expected at all and you could say okay
something strange happened let's go back
to the ground or you could say huh like
why did that happen um and it turns out
that the labs where when something
unexpected happens they follow up and
try and figure it out do better in the
long run than the labs where you're
doing the thing that you were supposed
to do okay I will try to let go of
graduate students as an example here and
and think more about the actual human
babies uh tell tell us more about how
they get their picture of the world I
know that one crucial step is when they
figure out that other people have
opinions or beliefs that are different
than their own yeah so the the big idea
about Child Development which now I and
other developmentalists have been
arguing for for the last I don't know 20
25 years is that you should think about
um development as being like Theory
formation in science and at first that
idea seems sort of unlikely I mean
little kids are they not like really
smart scientists but when you look
carefully at the way they understand the
world it looks a lot like the kinds of
theories and the changes in theories
that adults uh that scientists have and
what that suggests is that from a a kind
of computational perspective that's a
just a really good way of getting
information about the world so what
we've shown is that from the time
they're very very little children are
looking for causal relationships for
example which is one of the things that
real that's really important in a theory
and we can show again with our little
blicket detector these little machines
that have where they have unexpected
causal properties we can show that even
you know toddlers are doing the right
kinds of inferences about how those
kinds of systems work so they seem to
develop these causal models these kind
of what are sometimes called intuitive
theories um and then they get new data
and they change the theories depending
on the data and we can show that really
systematically so we can we can for
instance show them information data
about how that little little um uh about
how that little uh Machine Works the
little licket detector works and then we
can see what kinds of inferences do they
make into a remarkable degree they make
the inferences that you should make if
you're trying to if you were being a
good scientist but of course you know
figuring out how machines work is fine
but the thing that's most important in
all of our Lives arguably is figuring
out how the people around us are working
um so way back in the 80s I and others
um did developed what's come to be
called um theory of mind which is
figuring out what is it in baby's Minds
that enables them to understand your
mind and what we found out which is sort
of typical of what we found out is that
babies both know more to begin with than
we would have thought but they also
learn more um so between say one and two
for instance they seem to start learning
that people could want different things
I could want one thing you could want
another between uh four and six they
seem to start understand between three
and six they start to understand that I
could think something different than you
do and those are really really deep
important things to understand but more
recently one of the things that I think
has been very interesting is the
development of work on children's
intuitive sociology so they're also
figuring things out like oh when people
are allies they'll behave this way and
ah the next level good yeah right when
they're enemies then they'll behave this
other way and if one uh creature is
dominant is larger than the other then
they can get their way and what we're
just trying to do now again to go back
to this caregiving point is figure out
what do they actually think about
caregiving and there's a little bit of
evidence that even babies already are
identifying okay this is what it looks
like for someone to take care of someone
else this is a good potential this is a
good potential caregiver for me so
there's this lovely kind of back and
forth between that helplessness that I
talked about and then the fact that if
you are that kind of helpless creature
learning about other people learning
about love learning about what other
people are like is going to be really
important for your your survival and of
course as adults that's still the most
important thing that we learned about I
want to get the in the audience's mind
the idea of those blicket detector
clearly it's playing a big role in your
psychology experiments is this something
you buy off the shelf or do you make
them yeah it's funny we we started out
uh when we started doing this 20 years
ago um we actually made them so we had
in those days in the psychology
department you had a shop which we still
T to have anymore but we had a shop and
we went to the folks in the shop and
said okay well look here's what we want
we want this little it's just it's very
simple it's a little box you put
different things on top and sometimes it
lights up and plays music and sometimes
it doesn't and then we had various other
kinds of variants of this so we had one
with gears where you flick a switch and
then the gears go and then that make
something else happen so they're kind of
like uh rub little Rube Goldberg
machines that we'd we'd uh we'd put
together now at the time that we this is
a kind of interesting um anecdotal
observation at the time that we first
did this we thought gee this would be so
much easier to do if we just had screens
in a computer and you could do it that
way the kids didn't want to have
anything to do with when it was a a
screen they really needed to have the
real thing but now what we're finding is
that even like three and four-year olds
um and I think the big difference is now
screens are interactive so three and
foury olds have the idea and in fact
again if you have a a baby you know
really love the idea that they can act
on uh uh they can touch something they
can talk to it they can swipe it and
then figure out what the outcome uh is
supposed to be although it still looks
like we need the real things for the for
the younger kids but for the older kids
the older kids now sort of have the idea
oh okay a a a screen is something that
has causal Powers as well as a a little
machine does but still you have these
little you still doing the little boxes
I I just like the idea that it's a right
of passage in the gnik lab for graduate
students to build a little box that
lights up under different circumstances
well that's that's exactly right and we
have a lab culture about where we get
the doorbells that go in it and um one
of the funny uh a funny story about this
when we first started doing it um uh
when we first started doing it we
actually had the folks in the shop who
were who were putting these things
together and at one point one of the
machines that we had broke and my
brilliant graduate student and I went in
and asked said look it's not working the
you know the the gear is not making the
other gear go and they said oh no that's
not how it works we just programmed it
so it does this specific thing when you
so there's no there's actually no
physics behind it at all it's just a
it's like a you know it's like a Tesla
car it's just computer masquerading as a
a real physical artifact and we were I'm
have to say we were a bit crushed about
this also the way that it actually works
most of the time in the lab is that
there's a graduate student who's sitting
and pressing a button underneath the
table that's determining what
so from the kids perspective too it's
not they're they have the illusion of
actually doing physics but what they're
actually chewing is doing experiments It
Feels Like The Wizard of Oz here I feel
like I've been fooled about all this all
this stuff going on okay so uh if you
say things like you know a child under
one-year-old doesn't have this theory of
mind and a two-year-old does so do we
know of certain benchmarks or phase
transitions in the growth of a child
where there you know cognitive view of
the world expands a bit Yeah so as I say
from the very beginning I mean literally
from the time they're born babies are
doing things like paying special
attention to faces and interpreting them
from very early on they're imitating
other people in a way that other
primates don't seem to which suggests
that there's something about
understanding other people that's really
important um by the time they're nine
months old they're doing things like
pointing to communicate and a
9-month-old will point and if you don't
follow the point they'll get ansy and go
you know dare dare dare um so that
suggests that they know something about
what the fact that other people are are
looking at the same thing that they are
um so sometimes what happens is that
people say oh you don't get theory of
mind until you're you're four or five
but that's not right you just get
different theories the same way you
would if you thought about you know
physics there's different kinds of
theories about different parts of of the
Mind
um uh what but very characteristically
you see these changes coming at you know
round about a particular age so about
nine months you see this big
Revolution and you know some of it may
just be maturation but I think the
something that is increasingly important
and that we haven't thought about enough
is just how active Learners even these
very young children are just how much
what they're doing is not just observing
statistics although of course they they
do that but but also actively
experimenting on the world and you know
if you think about even a newborn
they're looking at you they're smiling
they're seeing what the effects of their
actions are and by the time by the time
you're talking about um uh toddler
that's like their whole lives right
they're just constantly constantly doing
experiments except when they do it we
call it getting into everything um when
physicists do it we call it being a good
experimental physicist
um uh and I think it's really under so
one of the things that we've been doing
a lot recently is trying to think about
how the children's learning compares to
the learning of uh machines for example
something like the large models that
have had so much U uh play so what's the
relationship between what AI is doing
and what these very little kids are
doing and I think one of the really big
Dimensions that makes the kids different
from their AI systems is that they are
going out and actively trying to get
information about the world and then
changing what they think based on the
information they get as opposed to the
large models for example that are
basically just it's it's interesting to
think about this in terms of cultural
transmission the large models I've
argued really what they do is just pick
out patterns in all the things that
other people have already have already
figured out so they're just doing the
imitation part of of cultural
transmission
um but the kids are actually going out
there and finding out things that are
new and experimenting and seeing new
outcomes and we think that may be really
The crucial thing that lets them learn
as much as they do as quickly as they do
and with as few calories as they do
compared to the compared to the AI
systems so it is a little bit like the
distinction in causal reasoning between
simply finding correlations versus being
interventionist about things right going
outside the data set and saying if I did
this what would happen next yeah that's
exactly right and uh um and we've for 20
years we've been collaborating with
actually philosophers of science and
computer scientists who've been trying
to figure out how do we do causal
inference in in science and one of the
really you know basic ideas is that you
can't or it's very difficult to do it
just by looking at patterns of
Statistics or correlation that you want
to make causal information es well what
makes a causal inference different from
just a correlation this is a an old
philosophical problem back to Hume and I
think the idea that's become most
prominent in philosophy of science and
seems intuitively and in science itself
is well okay if you want to really make
the causal inference you have to do an
experiment you have to actually
intervene do something in the world see
what the outcome is that's what makes
something uh causal and I think we've
been doing some work on this but I think
if you look at uh even quite young
babies um you know if you think about
something like a busy box a busy box is
a toy that you use for little babies
they're called busy boxes a busy box is
a is a thing that has lots of causal
possibilities where you can do lots of
experiments it's it's cheaper than your
you know standard cyclotron but it has
the same kind of character for babies it
it's a way of um it's a way of actually
being able to to do the kinds of
experiments that you need to figure out
how the world works and of course as I
point out the since um theory of mind
and intuitive psychology is so important
they have a great experimental subject
there all the time which is the
caregiver so if you think about them as
being little scient little psychologists
we're the labrats so a lot of what
babies do the ter in the Terrible Twos
for example is um doing something and
then looking to see how we uh react to
it you know we had uh Juda Pearl on the
podcast and at one point yeah and at one
point he said literally like haven't you
ever seen a baby all a baby is doing is
like touching things and making a causal
map of the world and I I understood what
he was saying and agreed with it but I
guess I I didn't realize it was quite as
literal as uh apparently it is no
absolutely so what we've done is taken
some of the formalisms that Pearl
developed like hle baset and then show
how the children are uh how the the ways
that children are solving these causal
problemss are just like uh what you'd
expect from causal graphical models so
essentially what the children I mean I
think we can say that we've demonstrated
this what the children are doing is
constructing causal uh graphical models
from data and then using them to
determine their interventions now the
thing is that both for Judea and for the
whole world of causal inference and for
us it's still a kind of Unsolved problem
about and for science ien right how do
you decide which experiment is really
the right experiment to do sure so what
something like um um Juda uh uh
framework lets you do is say okay if you
get this result here's the causal graph
you should have but how do you decide
what you should test in the first place
um and I think one interesting thing
that's coming out is that a lot of the
um the sort of old shth about how you do
experiments you have to keep everything
constant you can only vary one thing at
a time that may that's not true for
babies that it may not be the best way
of doing science either it and and I
think this is like a
wonderful um open uh a wonderful open
question about how do you decide what
kind of uh experiments to do how do you
decide how to explore and we've started
doing this with kids in um kids and AI
agents what we've done is put them in
the same kind of General environment um
uh Minecraft is one of the ones that we
use if you know M I imagine your
audience will know Minecraft although
there's a bit of a funny story about
this which is that um I originally
started doing this work about how you
explore the Minecraft environment
because my grandson was mad about
Minecraft and I figured well at least
this will make me cool right if I can
tell them the Grandma's doing stuff
about Minecraft um then I gave a big
talk about this I got something called
The Rumble heart prod it's a big deal
and my grandchildren were in the
audience and I said well I did this
because I wanted to impress Auggie and
he came up to me very sweetly after the
talk and said Grandma this is a little
that was a little embarrassing because
like nobody cool plays Minecraft anymore
we all play we all play fortnite um so
like it isn't really cool to be involved
in in Minecraft if you're a 13-year-old
so I I wasn't keeping up with the
changes but in any case Minecraft is a
great game it continues to be a great
game for for grown-ups and for 11y olds
and um and it's uh uh what we've done is
put kids in that environment and then
put AI agents in that environment and
just said figure out what's going on
explore and even relatively young kids
will explore that environment in a
rational way they're not just randomly
trying things they're doing things in a
way that lets them figure out how the
environment uh how the environment works
and they're much much much better at it
than AI agents are interesting well the
thing you said about traditional
scientific methodology asking us to keep
all but one thing constant and changing
that one thing and seeing what the
effective I mean that makes s that
sounds sensible to me uh but is it just
because it's simpler to keep track of
what's going on but maybe it's
ultimately less effective than kind of
poking things in concert yeah so that's
a really interesting technical formal
question about when you know that it is
true that if you did that that's a
simple normative rule about what to do
but sometimes actually doing trying to
vary different things at once can be
more informative than than because as
you can imagine it's really hard to keep
everything else constant and just change
one thing um and that that I think
thinking about what the kids are doing
can be very because the kids some the
kids are are often trying lots of
different things in different in
different ways if you think about you
know the 2-year-old with the busy box um
and yet they seem to be such good
Learners so it's a really interesting
question I think for AI for science for
developmental psychology about how
that's possible and how literally true
is it to describe these very young
children as good
basian yeah I think it is literally true
um uh We've what we've done is take
various kinds of ideas from B an
inference and what we can do is give
kids information for instance about the
Baseline probability of a hypothesis and
then we can give them information that
will let them update that hypothesis and
they'll do the right kind of updating in
the right kind of way there another kind
of discovery that was in my lab but also
even more in Labs like uh Richard asand
and Jenny saffrons back in the 90s was
that children are quite good at doing
statistics which you might be really
surprised at because after all grown-ups
are notoriously bad at doing
probabilities but if you do something
like um show the children that one
blicket works um eight out of 10 times
and the other one works four out of 10
times um they'll pick the one that has a
higher probability of activate and then
this is with 18month olds and then you
say okay which one will you use here
make the machine go they'll pick the one
that has the higher statistical
probability in fact they'll do it even
if it's like 2/3 versus 8/10 so they
seem to be able to kind of do the math
implicitly obviously and unconsciously
to figure out what how probabilities
work so you know there there's and but
again this has led to this puzzle which
is they really seem to be doing
something like basian inference and yet
we know that basian inference ideally is
sort of impossible computationally so if
you have a if you have a big set of
hypotheses then it's going to take you
you know if you the the basian idea is
you take a hypothesis you generate a
pattern of evidence you check it against
the data that you've got you figure out
which hypothesis would have been most
likely to generate that pattern of data
um and the problem is if you have a big
space of hypotheses that's just going to
take forever because you're going to
have to try each one of the hypotheses
separately it's called the search
problem and nobody's really quite solved
that problem either in statistic or in
AI or in childhood and the children do
seem to be able to solve that problem
because they end up you know finding out
about the world and it's a really
interesting question about how they
solve it and my guess at the moment is
that something about this active
inference might be part of the solution
that it isn't just that you're sort of
sitting back having data float over you
and then trying to update your
hypothesis you're actually out there
being an experimentor and figuring
things out um uh which should make at
least the you I know that when in
physics there's always a bit of a
tension between the theoreticians and
the experimentalists so um I think from
the developmental perspective we're
we're team experimentalists that's the
the fair enough that's that's that looks
like that's really the secret and how
much do we know about the Neuroscience
of this kind of thing I mean are these
ideas that babies sort of get better at
different kinds of reasoning as they
grow older mirrored in ways that the
brain is wiring itself yeah it's quite
neat because one of the oldest uh
developmental Neuroscience findings
which is consistent with what we've
we've seen to this day is that
um early in development what you see is
lots of new synapses lots of new
connections being formed and then
there's a point a kind of Tipping Point
where the ones connections that have
been formed formed are strengthened
they're melinated they become more
effective the ones that haven't been
formed are pruned so the weaker ones
just kind of disappear so you have this
early brain that is very very flexible
very good at changing in the light of
new experience very plastic as
neuroscientists say and then but not
very effective right not very good at
actually doing anything and then you
have this later brain that's very good
at doing things but much less good at
changing much less with much less ptic
City and again this is like another
version of this explore exploit
trade-off and empirically if you look at
brain development you can see that
depending on the domain that you're in
you see this pattern of very early um
early proliferation and then later
pruning so if you look at the visual
system for instance you see this Tipping
Point at around 18 months so the visual
system is Du getting set in that early
period and then it kind of settles in
which is why uh if you have vision
problems it's really important to
correct them in a baby it's really
important to correct them early if you
look at the language areas it's like
five or six where you start seeing this
you start seeing this transition so it's
when you've developed a language that
then it becomes harder for you to learn
another um uh learn a new language um
and if you look at what sometimes called
the executive function the prefrontal
part of the brain that's the latest one
and that's not completely getting set
until adolescence for example um okay so
you you see this but you do see this
General pattern of start out with lots
and lots of connections and then at some
point start strengthening and
pruning and I I just hate to bring it
back to Academia once again but this
this comports with the idea that you
know like the energetic young idea
creators are the young faculty in
postdocs right not the uh older senior
faculty you've been successful for many
decades yeah I mean I think it's a an
obvious question that lots of people
have have asked is well are there things
that grown-ups could do that would make
them as creative as the uh as the
children and the first thing to say is
even if you're thinking about a lab if
you want to get grant money it's really
good to have people who are really
really practiced and and know how that
system works and are really good at and
even if you forget about grant money
just you know actually doing the
experiments if you're a physicist for
example is a giant you know Enterprise
it's really takes a lot of focus and
executive energy to be able to get the
experiments to run um so I don't think
you'd want you know like you don't want
your your department chair to be this
wild wildly creative person who's
thinking up strange ideas all the time
right you want them to be to be focused
nevertheless I think it's interesting
that and and relevant to this explor
expl tradeoff that um when adults want
to adults often will kind of have social
institutions that allow them to switch
back and forth between this um explore
and exploit so sabatical I think are a
great example in the academic context
right so we don't sort of expect
scientists to be able to just do this on
their own what we think is going off to
a retreat going off to a sabatical going
off to a workshop those are all ways
that you can kind of pull yourself out
of the context that you're already in
and and allow yourself to to do greater
um exploration so you know it's a pain
that we all spend so much time traveling
as scientists but I do think there's a
bit of an argument that being in a
different place being in a different
context often doing interdisciplinary
work where you're you're you're forced
to think about things in really
different ways because now you're
looking at biologists instead of
physicists all those seem to be ways
that grown-ups set themselves up to be
more creative
and does it you've mentioned already
several times the connection between um
these ideas and AI large language models
Etc how operationalizable are these
insights can we imagine building better
AI models using this uh the lessons
we've learned from
development well that's kind of what
we've been doing so um I'm part of the
Berkeley AI research group and um and
what we're trying to do is take some of
these ideas IDE about Active Learning
ideas about social learning ideas about
causal model build building and actually
Implement them in in the in in AI
systems and you know to a certain extent
what's happened is that because the
large models have been so effective in
lots of ways um they've there's a
tendency to sort of say okay well they
worked before we'll just keep make we'll
just you know pour more uh compute into
them and they'll get bigger and they'll
use up more energy and then we'll
they'll get better and better and we'll
have this mythical thing called AGI and
one of the things when I talk to AI
groups which I do a lot now I have a um
I have a um uh a slide where I say
there's no such thing as general
intelligence artificial or natural which
always leads to Sharp and take of breath
from uh from the audience because it
isn't the the the theory the the
ideology the model and oh okay there's
this one this gets back to our very
first conversation the model that
there's this one thing called
intelligence some people have more of it
some people have less of it if you have
more and more of it then you're going to
be more and more effective right that's
not the model that comes out of
cognitive science at all what comes out
of cognitive science is that we have
these trade-offs between different kinds
of of cognitive capacities so if we
could design sorry so llms don't rather
strikingly have any of these Capac
they're not going out in the world and
doing experiments um they're not
creating um abstract caal models that
then they can use to generalize and you
can see the difference between the
amount of data that the children have
and how good they are at generalizing it
to new situations and and the large
models the large models need enormous
amounts of data and they're not very
good at generalizing especially to
what's called out of distribution cases
cases that weren't there in their
training the kids are ve with much less
data are very good at doing that so the
question is what what are the kids doing
and could that make more effective Ai
and I think the thing to say at the
moment is we're very very if you start
thinking about the comparison to kids
we're very very far away so um they're
they're the kids are you know orders and
Orders of magnitude better than any of
the current AI uh systems that we have
but I think that's the direction that we
might want to go in well it it's a
difficult conversation to have sometimes
because the AI um the people who worry
that we're close to Super intelligence
any moment now will say look the you
know we can beat the best human beings
at playing chess or playing go or
whatever and and you try to make the
point as as you just did that there are
other aspects of intelligence that
they're not good at but it's they seem a
little bit fuzzier right it's it's quite
it's a little bit harder to put a
benchmark on it is that something that
we're trying to make progress on well I
mean one thing is that uh for example if
you look at
robotics um the you know
notoriously the the uh the AIS are
better at playing chess but they're
terrible at actually picking up the
pieces if you if you made part of the
game be that you had to pick up find the
pieces in a you know that have spilled
on the floor and put them back in
exactly the right places they're really
quite bad at doing that especially if
you had say a new chest set that was uh
you know like a an Allison Wonderland
chess set or something where where it
wasn't you couldn't you couldn't just
identify them from your previous
training um and this is the famous
maravich's Paradox this goes back to
beginnings of AI that uh things that
look really hard for hum chess and go
turn out to be relatively easy for AI
and things that look really easy like
perception and action and movement and
the kinds of things that kids do when
they figure out how the little blicket
detector Works turn out to be really
hard for um for AI I I think the whole
conversation about intelligence in AI is
fundamentally misguided because really
the reason why the systems are as
effective as they are is because they're
taking advantage of you know hundreds of
thousands of humans who've done things
like put text on the web and uh um
and in some ways like with reinforcement
learning from Human feedback have
trained up the systems um my my latest
metaphor about this is do you know the
story of Stone Soup the old children's
story of Stone Soup yeah this is a
wonderful children's story this is
another advantage of being a
developmental psychologist is um you
have wisdom of the stories that
grandmothers have told in the past so
this turns out to be a very very
widespread bit of folklore um and here's
the story there's these visitors who
come to um a village and they say we
want some food in the villagers say oh
sorry we don't have any we can't share
any with you and the visitors say that's
okay we're going to make stone soup we
have magic Stones so they get a big
cauldron they put this couple of stones
in The Cauldron it starts boiling they
say see we're just going to make stone
soup it's so good you know it would be
even better if we had an onion and a
carrot that we could put in it um but I
guess if we don't have it we don't have
it so one of the Villager says I I think
I have an onion and a carrot somewhere
they go and put it in they say oh that's
great like oh see how well this soup is
working um when we made it for the king
we put a chicken in and that was really
great so could you go and and of course
you can guess what happens the the
villagers all contribute their bit of of
uh their bit of food and then at the end
the villagers say this is amazing this
is Magic we got all this soup just from
a stone and I think if you think about a
version of that where you said there
were the computer people um The Tech
Guys who went to the universe of
computer users and said oh we have AGI
we can do it just with you know three
algorithms gradient descent and
Transformers and we'll have AGI any
minute now um but you know we really
need a lot of data to make this AGI work
and the users said oh okay we have all
of our text and pictures that we put on
the internet all of our books all of our
newspapers um we could give you that to
make the intelligence and then the the
villagers the The Tech Guys say uh
oh that's really great but like if we
could do reinforcement the our AGI is
still saying stupid things so if we
could get reinforcement learning from
Human feedback and and get people to
give us feedback about whether our AGI
is doing well or not that would make it
even better um and the people said oh
okay like there's whole villages in
Kenya who could do this and finally the
tech gu said oh that's really we're
getting really good intelligence but if
we could do prompt engineering so we
could figure out what exactly what
prompt to use
that would make it even more intelligent
could you do that and the user say oh
yeah we could think a lot about that and
then of course in the end what happens
is that the the tech gu say see we told
you we made AI just from a couple of
algorithms um and it's ignoring the fact
that the reason why it works is not
because of the algorithms but because of
the data and that data comes from a
bunch of humans who are doing the kind
of exploratory creative intelligence
that four-year-olds do I do presume that
there are other angles on building AI
systems that that are more oriented
towards making causal models of the
world even intervening putting them in
robots I really I really don't know yeah
that's one of the things that people
have thought about but as I say it's
hard so you know trying to do the basian
inference is hard because the search
problem is hard um there's what's called
reinforcement learning and reinforcement
learning old idea in Psychology is the
and actually take actions and then see
if the actions make you better off or
not so you know the mouse who runs
through the Maze and um um uh gets
cheese sometimes but gets a shock other
times right um and learns to go towards
the cheese and away from the shock so
that's a technique that for example in
the um go uh solution reinforcement
learning played a really important uh
role in in trying to solve that problem
so the chess
uh the the chess agent is playing
against itself over many many trials to
try and figure out what the what the
best reinforcement learning is but the
problem with reinforcement learning is
that it it's too narrow like if you just
end up on you could since all you're
thinking about is am I better off or not
you're not going to be able to do the
kind of exploration that you need to
really figure out how the world Works um
and so the idea that I think is most
promising and we've been working on
is an idea that should be very familiar
from science which is an idea that you
could do learning but instead of instead
of trying to calculate whether you've
got you know higher usefulness or
utility or not or whether you got more
cheese what you're calculating is did I
get more information did I find out more
about the world or did I find out more
about the system when I when I did this
action versus this other action and the
result is that you are going to do again
to go back to the point we made before
you're going to do the things that will
tell you something about how the world
works even if they don't make you any
better off in the in the short run um
and there are ideas in uh an idea I
really like and that we've been working
on is the idea of a kind of intrinsic
reward like the kind of reward you get
as a scientist when you when you just
are doing it because it's so cool when
things work out the way that you want so
I think the solution to the problem
means having a kind of reinforcement
learning uh agent but one where the
reward isn't cheese or utility or
winning the game it's finding out
something new figuring out more about
how the world works and there's been a
lot of interesting attempts both in
development and in AI to figure out how
you could make that happen what kind of
signal would tell you that as a result
of this action you'd learn more and one
that we're working on now that I think
is really interesting is something
called empowerment and the idea behind
empowerment is that you get rewarded
when you do something and it has a
predictable effect on the world so what
you do is try to do as many things as
you can where varying the action that
you take will vary what happens out
there in the world and when you do that
that's really exciting that's really
cool that is something you're going to
be likely to try again but you also want
as many different kinds of actions as
many different relationships like that
as you can so if you find one after a
while you'll get bored and you'll try
and find uh you'll try and find another
one and I think that's very closely
related to the causal learning that I
talked about before so if you think
about what you you mentioned this Sean
that causation is all about intervention
right so really what you're learning
with this empowerment reward is I'm
going to learn how to intervene I'm
going to learn how doing things out
there in the world ends up having ends
up having um uh effects and we have a
little bit of evidence that even tiny
babies you know if you take literally a
two or three-month-old and you put a
ribbon between their foot and a mobile
so that they can actually control what
happens to the mobile they'll sit there
and try all sorts of different patterns
of kicking to try and see what the
consequences are going to be for the
mobile so they really are like little
and they'll smile and they'll Giggle and
they'll go back to doing it it just
seems to be an incredibly satisfying uh
an incredibly satisfying Enterprise for
them and of course they're doing the
same thing with Mom when they're you
know doing all sorts of funny faces and
seeing if mom gives funny faces back
again um so I think that might be a
really really important part of the
solution and again it speaks to science
because going back to what we were
saying before about how systematic do
your experiments have to be um one of
the things that I've noticed is that the
powers that be always say well you don't
want to just have a fish fishing
Expedition right this grant is just a
fishing Expedition but a a lot of times
what you actually end up doing is doing
a fishing Expedition you you try
something and then uh kind of
unexpectedly it has this particular
systematic result and that's the that's
the where the gold is rather than the
causation that you already that you
already know about and empowerment is
kind of a way of saying yeah get keep
that fishing expedition going well and
there are better and worse ways to go
fishing right exactly exactly you know
we did have Carl friston also on the
podcast
and he has these ideas of the free
energy principle and the basian brain
and and part of it part of the sort of
aspect that gives people pause is he
seems to be saying that our brains try
to minimize being surprised and you
might think that therefore you should
just sit in a dark room and never do
anything but if I understand correctly
he was saying no actually we want to
minimize the net surprise over our lives
and therefore we better explore around
and do weird things now so we can
anticipate what's coming yeah that's
exactly like the exploration
exploitation um trade-off that I was
talking about so it's it's interesting
if you think about something like uh
empowerment or all of these kind of
intrinsic rewards the failure cases are
you just sit there and do the same thing
over and over again and maybe those are
human failure cases too um so you need
to do is to be able to want to have a
coherent story about what's going on
around you you don't want to just be uh
you don't want to just be paying
attention to random stuff that's
happening yeah um even though that might
give you something that's new and
surprising um but you also don't want to
just do the same thing over and over
again and and we've been looking at you
know comparing for instance what do
children think when you give them a
machine that just randomly does
different things like our our blicket
detector but a kind of random blicket
detector versus one where there's a
systematic relationship between what you
do and what comes out even if what comes
out is surprising versus one that just
does something obvious that you know
about beforehand and they really seem to
like to play with the machine that that
is surprising but surprising in a
systematic way and I think that's true
about scientists too the world has some
structure and we do take advantage of
that and I think this is something that
we haven't quite uh as philosophers
physicists AI researchers whatever uh
learned how to systematize perfectly
yeah I mean one of the things that that
always strikes me I mean the reason why
I started doing this work in the first
place back when I was a philosophy
student completely a philosophy student
is if you think about um you know going
back to Plato and Aristotle one of the
deep philosophical questions is this
question of knowledge it's how we know
that there's a world out there it has
structure not only does have it has you
know quirks and minds and all sorts of
things that we can't immediately observe
in it and yet all that reaches us from
that world is a bunch of disturbances of
air at our eardrums and photons at our
eyes how do we ever at any point manage
to reconstruct that world from that data
and I think going back to Plato and
Aristotle the two ways of trying to
answer that question have been to say
well okay it just looks as if we're
understanding that world from data it's
really there all along so it's really
some kind of inate there's some kind of
innate evolved structure that's
responsible uh for this and that's been
one that's Plato's approach that's
that's one of the approaches the other
approach going back to Aristotle which
is the approach of the most recent
version of AI like the llms is it just
looks as if we're really understanding
the structure all we're doing is pulling
out correlations between those photons
and those disturbances of a so all we're
doing is just taking the data and
pulling out correlations and we think
that that's telling us something about
structure but but we have no particular
reason to think that and the great thing
about development is that if you look at
actual babies and children actually
learning they don't seem to fit either
of those pictures they seem to be able
to learn really and I think also if you
look at science um we seem to be able to
learn really radically new things about
the world whether it's learning that I
might like broccoli and you don't or
whether it's learning about uh you know
uh corks and and leptons um and and yet
it doesn't look as if all we're doing is
just pulling together the finding
statistical correlations in the data it
looks as if we're genuinely developing
theories that go beyond just the
correlations in the data and I I don't
think we have a good it you know even
though we've been doing this for a
thousand years we still don't have a
good formal model computational model
good understanding of how that's
possible and I think looking at the kids
who are clearly doing it is is a really
good route to answering that
philosophical question and that's what
I've spent my whole career do it you
know sometimes looking at what actually
happens in the world does help us
understand it better
Alison gnik thanks so much for being on
the mindcap podcast well thanks so much
for having me Shan a great conversation
[Music]